The second approach and the more modern approach to applying AI for theorem proving is like it started like maybe five years ago or four years ago and it's based on deep learning and more and more on larger language models.
So a few years ago, companies like DeepMind and startups like Harmonic and Acimeth started trying out modern deep learning and how to use it to automate mathematics or to automate theorem proving in general.
And in 2025, those companies have reached a milestone that would have been impossible to imagine like just two years ago, which is, or three years ago, which is that they solved, which is that they got the gold, for example, they got the gold medal in the international math.
So then Piazza, which was a milestone that just sounded like a science fiction two years ago. And for those companies that do, that build, so basically what are those companies doing? They're building specialized machine learning models just for theorem proving.
So they have like an entire training set up just for theorem proving. So what is the idea of that? So basically they do reinforcement learning.
A lot of them or most of them doing reinforcement learning. So the way you started reinforcement learning, so basically you have a policy and then you get, and then that policy is basically a function that you give it a mathematical goal and then it comes up with a proof.
And then the policy is, the proof that's generated by the policy is given to a theorem prover like Isabelle, for instance, or Lean or something else. And then that theorem prover takes, that the prover confirms what the policy generated, if it confirms the correctness.
So basically the policy generates an Isabelle proof, in our case, and then Isabelle checks that proof, if the proof works, then you give a positive reward, otherwise you give a zero reward.
And using that reward, the policy is updated to either confirm that this direction in which it's going is correct, and it should follow the current approach.
And if the proof fails, then it should go in another direction, basically. So it's a basic reinforcement learning loop, but there is a very big problem with that for us and for the scientific community and for you as students and so forth.
Which is that doing this reinforcement learning loop for mathematics, we need enormous GPU clusters which cost hundreds of millions of dollars.
So usually the pre-training, like the reinforcement learning stage costs minimum five million to one hundred million dollars, and then some more millions for fine tuning, and so it's extremely, extremely expensive and inaccessible.
So that was the first trial, that was the first successful trial of newer machine learning approaches here. Here, of course, this policy model is a deep learning model.
So the reason this whole thing started was because of deep learning and the ability to use deep learning models as policies in reinforcement learning.
So as I mentioned in the previous case, like on the previous slide, that approach of building custom models is extremely expensive and inaccessible.
Another approach, which is actually the one that we may be using here, and which is the one that really caused a revolution in how theorem proving is done, is using off-the-shelf coding agents to do mathematics.
You don't need to build a specialized agent for mathematics, that's what turns out to be the case.
All what you need to do is just a coding agent and then you connect it to a theorem prover, or even you don't need to connect it.
Like, for example, in the case of Isabelle, you don't need to connect it to a theorem prover in any sophisticated way.
Joseph Orban, in the beginning of 2026, showed that you can use CLOD or codecs or any of these frontier agents to develop very large formal proofs.
How did he do that? He simply gave the coding agent instructions that, okay, you write, and Isabelle's theory, where you prove, for example, in his case, he was formalizing an entire book.
So he had an entire informal textbook on topology. He turned it into a formal Isabelle theory that is like 250,000 lines.
And how did he do that? He simply told the agent, you should formalize the theorems in this book and solve the exercises.
And whenever you're done with a theorem or a lemma, you should use Isabelle's bill to confirm that it's correct.
And with this very simple loop, he was able to formalize the whole book with just a subscription that costs $200 a month.
So that might seem expensive, but it actually is much, much cheaper than what you would have to do with specialized models.
Now, more recently, to improve the efficiency of this loop, instead of just asking the coding agent to connect, to use Isabelle Build,
people have developed a model context protocol, so an MCP server for Isabelle and for others to improve.
And this replaces command line interface graphs loops, like using Isabelle Build, with basically that MCP server.
That MCP server gives the LLM or the coding agent a view of Isabelle corresponding to what you as a user see.
So, for example, this MCP server has a tool, you can use it to check for errors, you can use it to check for stories,
you can use it to call sledgehammer, you can use it to call auto, you can use it to check for warnings and so forth.
So basically, the coding agent using that MCP server connected to Isabelle can get a live vision of what's happening in Isabelle,
as if it's you, a human, developing an Isabelle theory directly.
Instead of the previous approach, or a more basic approach of just writing to the disk and then calling Isabelle Build,
this approach connects the agent to Isabelle using an MCP server, and there is another one for all other existing theorem provers as well.
So there are two types, there are two MCP servers developed that were developed for Isabelle.
One of them is called P2MCP and the other one is called Isabelle Queue.
The first one was done as part of a project in which I'm currently involved and I'm a pretty good investigator.
And the other one was done by AWS.
I would just use the first one, P2MCP, for my demos, but you can of course also try out the one-developer AWS if you want.
So now, let me show you how to connect Isabelle to, how to connect the coding agent to Isabelle by an MCP server.
So that will be the next demo here.